<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <head>
            M.R. SHAH, J.<lb/></head>

        <p>1.<lb/>
            Present application is preferred by the Union of India-Ministry of<lb/>
            Home Affairs with the following prayers:-<lb/></p>
<list>
        <item>&quot;(a) Modify the order dated 30.06.2021 and other<lb/>
            subsequent orders passed by this Hon&apos;ble Court in the<lb/>
            captioned matter permitting any central agency to<lb/>
            undertake a sample scrutiny to verify the claimed<lb/>
            documents processed by respective State Governments<lb/>
            for grant of ex gratia payment and take steps thereafter in<lb/>
            accordance with the law.<lb/></item>


        <item>(b) Modify the order dated 30.06.2021 and other<lb/>
            subsequent orders passed by this Hon&apos;ble Court in the<lb/>
            captioned matter to the extent of declaring time limit of<lb/>
            four weeks, from the date of order passed by this Hon&apos;ble<lb/>
            Court in the instant application, as an outer limit for the<lb/>
            existing eligible claimants to lodge their claims with the<lb/>
            authorities for seeking grant of ex gratia payment under<lb/>
            the orders of this Hon&apos;ble Court dated 30.06.2021 and a<lb/>
            time of four weeks for claimants who might become<lb/>
            eligible in the future;&quot;<lb/></item>
</list>
        <p>2.<lb/>
            Shri Tushar Mehta, learned Solicitor General has submitted that<lb/>
            after the order was passed by this Court dated 30.06.2021 and other<lb/>
            subsequent orders, the concerned States have received approximately<lb/>
            7,38,610 claims claiming ex-gratia compensation on the death of their<lb/>
            family members, who are entitled to the same pursuant to the order<lb/>
            passed by this Court dated 30.06.2021 and the subsequent orders. It is<lb/>
            submitted that since the COVID-19 pandemic in the country has now<lb/>
            subsided over the period of time since this Hon&apos;ble Court passed the<lb/>
            order dated 30.06.2021 and the subsequent order dated 29.11.2021, by<lb/>
            now, all genuine claimants must have approached the authorities by<lb/>
            establishing their claims. It is submitted that therefore it is not desirable<lb/>
            to continue the process of submitting/receiving the claims without any<lb/>
            outer time limit. It is submitted that if no outer limit of time is fixed, in that<lb/>
            case, there is a greater possibility of making false claims. Therefore, it is<lb/>
            prayed to determine the deadline before which the claimants of persons<lb/>
            who died due to COVID-19 can approach the authority making their<lb/>
            claims.<lb/>
            Shri Mehta, learned Solicitor General has suggested fixing the<lb/>
            deadline of four weeks to claim the ex gratia payment from the<lb/>
            authorities in case of death due to COVID-19.<lb/></p>

        <p>2.1 Shri Mehta, learned Solicitor General has further submitted that<lb/>
            there are genuine apprehensions of submitting fake claims in some of<lb/>
            the States. Therefore, it is prayed that there should be an audit and/or<lb/>
            at-least random scrutiny of the claim applications filed in the respective<lb/>
            States. Shri Mehta, learned Solicitor General has submitted that<lb/>
            receiving the ex-gratia compensation by making a false claim or<lb/>
            submitting fake/false certificate is a very serious matter. It is submitted<lb/>
            that even as per Section 52 of the Disaster Management Act, 2005<lb/>
            (hereinafter referred to as &quot;Act, 2005&quot;), making a false claim for obtaining<lb/>
            any relief under the Act, 2005 is a punishable offence. It is brought to<lb/>
            our notice that as of now approximately 7,38,610 claims are received<lb/>
            and, therefore, it may be very difficult to verify each and every claim. It<lb/>
            is submitted that therefore let there be a random sample scrutiny.<lb/></p>

        <p>2.1.1 Shri R. Basant, learned Senior Advocate appearing on behalf of<lb/>
            the State of Kerala and Andhra Pradesh, Shri Rahul Chitnis, learned<lb/>
            counsel appearing on behalf of the State of Maharashtra have also<lb/>
            supported Shri Tushar Mehta, learned Solicitor General and have<lb/>
            welcomed the sample scrutiny to find out the persons, who have made<lb/>
            false claims.<lb/></p>

        <p>3.<lb/>
            Having heard Shri Mehta, learned Solicitor General on the request<lb/>
            and the prayer made in the application and considering the fact that<lb/>
            more than nine months have passed after the first judgment and order<lb/>
            and thereafter four months have passed after the subsequent judgment<lb/>
            and order dated 29.11.2021 passed by this Court and by now<lb/>
            approximately 7,38,610 claims have been received by the concerned<lb/>
            States, Shri Mehta, learned Solicitor General is right in submitting that by<lb/>
            now all genuine claimants must have approached the authorities by<lb/>
            establishing their claims. He is also right in apprehending that if there is<lb/>
            no outer time limit fixed, then the process of receiving the claims would<lb/>
            go endless and, in that case, there is all possibility of submitting false<lb/>
            claims. However, at the same time, four weeks&apos; time suggested by Shri<lb/>
            Mehta, learned Solicitor General is too short. The family would need<lb/>
            some reasonable time to recover from the death and sorrow and filing<lb/>
            the claim. Therefore, we deem it appropriate to fix the outer limit of sixty<lb/>
            days from today to file the claims for compensation in case the death<lb/>
            occurred due to COVID-19 prior to 20.03.2022. For future deaths, ninety<lb/>
            days&apos; time is provided from the date of death due to COVID-19 to file the<lb/>
            claim for compensation. The earlier order to process the claims and to<lb/>
            make the actual payment of compensation within a period of thirty days<lb/>
            from the date of receipt of claim is ordered to be continued.<lb/></p>

        <p>4.<lb/>
            However it is clarified that in case of extreme hardship any<lb/>
            claimant could not make an application within the time prescribed, it will<lb/>
            be open for the claimant to approach the Grievance Redressal<lb/>
            Committee and make the claim through Grievance Redressal Committee<lb/>
            which shall be considered by the Grievance Redressal Committee on<lb/>
            case to case basis and if it is found by the Grievance Redressal<lb/>
            Committee that a particular claimant could not make the claim within the<lb/>
            stipulated time which was beyond their control his/her case may be<lb/>
            considered on merits.<lb/></p>

        <p>5.<lb/>
            Ministry of Health and Family Welfare and Ministry of Home Affairs<lb/>
            -Union of India and all the concerned States are directed to give wide<lb/>
            publicity to the present order through print and electronic media so that<lb/>
            the claimants can know the time limit fixed by this Court for making<lb/>
            claims. Such advertisement shall be published fortnightly for a period of<lb/>
            six weeks from today.<lb/></p>

        <p>6.<lb/>
            Now, so far as the allegation of submitting fake claims on<lb/>
            submitting false certificates or obtaining the compensation on submitting<lb/>
            the false claim is concerned, it is required to be noted that making a<lb/>
            false claim and obtaining any relief on that basis is a punishable offence<lb/>
            under Section 52 of the Act, 2005, which reads as under:-<lb/></p>

        <item>&quot;52. Punishment for false claim.-Whoever knowingly<lb/>
            makes a claim which he knows or has reason to believe<lb/>
            to be false for obtaining any relief, assistance, repair,<lb/>
            reconstruction or other benefits consequent to disaster<lb/>
            from any officer of the Central Government, the State<lb/>
            Government, the National Authority, the State Authority or<lb/>
            the District Authority, shall, on conviction be punishable<lb/>
            with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two<lb/>
            years, and also with fine.&quot;<lb/></item>

        <p>6.1 Nobody can be permitted to avail the ex-gratia compensation by<lb/>
            making a false claim and/or submitting the false certificate. A claimant is<lb/>
            entitled to the ex-gratia of Rs.50,000/-being a kin/family member of<lb/>
            those, who died due to COVID-19. Earlier, this Court passed the order<lb/>
            directing the Union of India/NDMA/concerned States to pay ex-gratia<lb/>
            amount keeping in mind the humanity and keeping in mind the sufferings<lb/>
            of the family members who lost one of their family members due to<lb/>
            COVID-19. Therefore, nobody can be permitted to misuse the same and<lb/>
            it is also against morality and is unethical, which can never be accepted.<lb/>
            Therefore, to start with a random scrutiny of the 5% of the claim<lb/>
            applications filed in the States of Andhra Pradesh, Gujarat, Kerala and<lb/>
            Maharashtra shall be made at the first instance. We permit the<lb/>
            NDMA/Union of India, through Ministry of Health and Family Welfare, to<lb/>
            carry out the random scrutiny of 5% of the claim applications by the<lb/>
            States of Andhra Pradesh, Gujarat, Kerala and Maharashtra at the first<lb/>
            instance. The concerned States are directed to assist in carrying out the<lb/>
            scrutiny of the claim applications as ordered above and submit all the<lb/>
            necessary particulars of the respective claims that have been<lb/>
            attended/processed to the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare, who<lb/>
            shall carry out the scrutiny within a period of three months from today<lb/>
            and submit the report before this Court. If it is found that anybody has<lb/>
            made a fake claim, the same shall be considered under Section 52 of<lb/>
            the Act, 2005 and liable to be punished accordingly.<lb/>
            Present application is accordingly disposed of in terms of the<lb/>
            above directions.<lb/></p>

        <p>………………………………….J.<lb/>
            [M.R. SHAH]<lb/>
            NEW DELHI;<lb/>
            ………………………………….J.<lb/>
            MARCH 24, 2022.<lb/>
            [B.V. NAGARATHNA]<lb/></p>

        <item>7</item>


    </text>
</tei>
