<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>NONREPORTABLE
            <lb/>IN THE SUPREME COURT OF INDIA
            <lb/>CIVIL APPELLATE JURISDICTION
            <lb/>M.A. Diary No.20972 of 2021
            <lb/>In
            <lb/>Civil Appeal No.9847 of 2014
            <lb/>INDIA POWER CORPORATION LTD.
            <lb/>…APPELLANT
            <lb/>VERSUS
            <lb/>EASTERN COALFIELDS LIMITED
            <lb/>RESPONDENT/
            <lb/>APPLICANT
            <lb/>

            J U D G M E N T
            <lb/>
        </front>

        <body>
            VIKRAM NATH, J.
            <lb/>
            1
            <lb/>Civil Appeal No.9847 of 2014 was allowed vide order dated
            <lb/>17.10.2014 whereby Justice S.S. Nijjar, a former Judge of this Court
            <lb/>was appointed as sole Arbitrator to arbitrate upon the disputes
            <lb/>between the parties. The said order is reproduced below:
            <lb/>&quot;
            <lb/>Leave granted.
            <lb/>Heard Mr. Kapil Sibal, learned senior counsel appearing
            <lb/>for the petitioner and Mr. Anupam Lal Das, learned counsel for
            <lb/>respondent no.1.
            <lb/>In the course of hearing, learned counsel for the parties
            <lb/>very fairly submitted that they have no objection if a former
            <lb/>
        </body>
        <page>1</page>
        <note place="footnote">
            <lb/>Signature Not Verified
            <lb/>Digitally signed by
            <lb/>Chetan Kumar
            <lb/>Date: 2022.03.15
            <lb/>16:48:21 IST
            <lb/>Reason:
        </note>

        <body>

            <lb/>Judge of this Court is appointed as a Sole Arbitrator to
            <lb/>arbitrate upon the disputes that have arisen in respect of the
            <lb/>contract.
            <lb/>Regard being had to the aforesaid submission, we
            <lb/>appoint Justice S.S. Nijjar, a former Judge of this Court as the
            <lb/>Sole Arbitrator to arbitrate upon the disputes. The learned
            <lb/>arbitrator shall decide the terms and conditions after
            <lb/>deliberating with the parties.
            <lb/>Registry is directed to forward a copy of this order to the
            <lb/>learned Arbitrator.
            <lb/>The appeal is allowed on above terms. There shall be no
            <lb/>order as to costs.&quot;
            <lb/>2.The sole Arbitrator gave the award dated 15.02.2021, after
            <lb/>
            considering the claims and counter claims of the parties. The operative
            <lb/>
            portion of the award as contained in paragraph 162 is reproduced
            <lb/>
            below:
            <lb/>&quot;162. In view of the aforesaid conclusions the following award
            <lb/>
            is made:
            <lb/>(a) The Respondent shall pay to the Claimant a sum of
            <lb/>
            Rs.24.7256 Crores as WDV.
            <lb/>(b) The aforesaid amount shall be paid with interest @9% with
            <lb/>
            effect from 06.10.2016 till payment of the amount.
            <lb/>(c) The Claimant shall pay to the Respondent a sum of
            <lb/>Rs.18,66,86,521/
            <lb/>(d) The aforesaid amount shall be paid with interest @9% with
            <lb/>effect from 06.10.2016 till payment of the amount.
            <lb/>(e) All other Claims and CounterClaims are hereby dismissed.
            <lb/>COSTS:
            <lb/>In the peculiar facts and circumstances of this
            <lb/>arbitration, both the parties shall bear their own costs.
            <lb/>This Award is being issued on a stamp paper of Rs.200/.
            <lb/>The Claimant shall pay the differential stamp duty in
            <lb/>accordance with law.&quot;
		</body>
		<page>
			2
		</page>
		<body>
		<lb/>3.
            <lb/>M.A. No. 20972 of 2021 has been filed by the respondent
            <lb/>&apos;Eastern Coalfields Limited&apos; (hereinafter referred to as the &quot;ECL&quot;) with
            <lb/>a prayer to appoint a sole arbitrator to examine the issue pertaining to
            <lb/>the report submitted by MECON as mentioned in paragraph 160 of the
            <lb/>award. The relief claimed by means of this application is reproduced
            <lb/>below:
            <lb/>&quot;PRAYER
            <lb/>In view of the facts and circumstances of the case, your
            <lb/>Lordship may graciously be pleased to:
            <lb/>a) Appoint a Sole Arbitrator to examine the issue pertaining to
            <lb/>the report submitted by MECON more particularly mentioned
            <lb/>in paragraph No.160 of the Award which was not adjudicated
            <lb/>by the Hon&apos;ble Tribunal;
            <lb/>b) Pass any other order/orders which this Hon&apos;ble Court may
            <lb/>deem fit.&quot;
            <lb/>4.
            <lb/>The only ground raised for seeking a fresh appointment of
            <lb/>Arbitrator is to the contents of paragraph 160 of the award. It is for
            <lb/>this reason that the present application has been filed for appointment
            <lb/>of Sole Arbitrator.
            <lb/>5.
            <lb/>According to the respondentapplicant, the learned Arbitrator
            <lb/>could not adjudicate upon the MECON report, as it required further
            <lb/>evidence to be recorded, and soon after delivering the award, on
            <lb/>15.02.2021, the learned Arbitrator died on 26.03.2021.
            <lb/>6.
            <lb/>Learned Counsel for the applicant, ECL during the course of the
            <lb/>arguments not only requested for appointment of Arbitrator with
            <lb/>respect to the contents of the paragraph 160 of the award but raised a
            <lb/></body>

        <page>3
            <lb/></page>

        <body>further issue relating to Section 33 of the Arbitration and Conciliation
            <lb/>Act, 1996 (hereinafter referred to as &apos;the 1996 Act&apos;) for requiring
            <lb/>correction in the computation of the rent payable to the applicant ECL
            <lb/>for the period March 2016 till October 2016 which was inadvertently
            <lb/>left out by the learned Arbitrator while giving the award. Reference
            <lb/>was made to paragraphs 126 to 130 and 132 of the award. It is also
            <lb/>submitted that although limitation for moving an application under
            <lb/>Section 33 is 30 days but in the present case as the limitation has
            <lb/>stopped running and stood extended by the orders passed by this
            <lb/>Court in the suo moto petition, the applicant would have a right to
            <lb/>maintain an application under Section 33 for correction of the award
            <lb/>for which the present application has been filed on 2 nd September,
            <lb/>2021.
            <lb/>7.
            <lb/>On the other hand, learned counsel for the appellant &apos;India
            <lb/>Power Corporation Limited&apos; (hereinafter referred to as the &quot;IPCL&quot;)
            <lb/>vehemently opposed the application and made the following
            <lb/>submissions:
            <lb/>i) Paragraph 160 of the award may not be read in
            <lb/>isolation. The background for the same should also be
            <lb/>read as recorded in the preceding and succeeding
            <lb/>paragraphs. Paragraphs 157 to 161 of the award may be
            <lb/>read as a whole. The same will completely clarify the
            <lb/>position.
            <lb/></body>

        <page>4
            <lb/></page>

        <body>ii) In the part covering paragraphs 157 to 161, the
            <lb/>learned Arbitrator was dealing with amendment of
            <lb/>counter claim filed by the respondentapplicant i.e. ECL.
            <lb/>After considering all aspects of the matter, the
            <lb/>application for amendment was dismissed as it would not
            <lb/>serve any useful purpose in determining the real question
            <lb/>in controversy. Reference may be had to paragraph 161
            <lb/>of the award.
            <lb/>iii) The contents of paragraph 160 of the award records
            <lb/>the submission advanced by the counsel for the claimant
            <lb/>i.e. the appellant IPCL. If paragraph 160 is examined
            <lb/>carefully, the submissions advanced by the counsel for
            <lb/>the respondentapplicant may not have much substance.
            <lb/>iv) Award dated 15.02.2021 was a final award and not
            <lb/>an interim award; The learned arbitrator had not left
            <lb/>anything for further deliberation but had settled the
            <lb/>claim and the counter claim between the parties in toto.
            <lb/>v) The remedy available to the respondentapplicant was
            <lb/>to file objections under Section 34 of the 1996 Act against
            <lb/>the award, if it had any grievance.
            <lb/>vi)
            <lb/>Further, the objection under Section 34 of the
            <lb/>1996 Act were filed before the Delhi High Court which
            <lb/>was registered as O.M.P.(COMM) 328/2021, CAV
            <lb/>49/2021, I.A. Nos. 1420414207/2021, Eastern
            <lb/></body>

        <page>5
            <lb/></page>

        <body>Coalfields Limited vs. India Power Corporation
            <lb/>Limited. The said objection has since been decided by
            <lb/>the Delhi High Court vide judgment dated 29.10.2021
            <lb/>and the same has been dismissed. A copy of the
            <lb/>judgment of Delhi High Court dated 29.10.2021 has been
            <lb/>filed
            <lb/>by
            <lb/>the
            <lb/>respondentapplicant
            <lb/>along
            <lb/>with
            <lb/>I.A.No.154735 of 2021.
            <lb/>vii)
            <lb/>The issue relating to Section 33 of the 1996 Act
            <lb/>with respect to correct computation of rent cannot be
            <lb/>considered for several reasons. There is not a whisper in
            <lb/>the application for direction regarding the issue raised
            <lb/>under Section 33. Such a plea cannot be raised during
            <lb/>the course of the arguments by way of oral or written
            <lb/>submissions.
            <lb/>viii)
            <lb/>Even otherwise no correction as raised was
            <lb/>required inasmuch as no computation was undertaken
            <lb/>by the learned Arbitrator and the amount awarded as
            <lb/>rent was the same as claimed by the applicant ECL.
            <lb/>Even on merits such plea was not tenable.
            <lb/>8.
            <lb/>Having considered the submissions, we now proceed to analyse
            <lb/>both the contentions of the applicant.
            <lb/></body>

        <page>6
            <lb/></page>

        <body>9.
            <lb/>Paragraph 160 of the award cannot be read in isolation. It was a
            <lb/>part of the award dealing with the &quot;Application for amendment of
            <lb/>counter claim&quot; filed by respondentECL. The award carried the above
            <lb/>subtitle before paragraph 157.
            <lb/>Paragraph 160 contains mere
            <lb/>submissions advanced on behalf of the appellant/claimant. MECON
            <lb/>report was called with respect to the amendment of the counter claim
            <lb/>regarding expenses required for putting the plant into running
            <lb/>condition. After deliberating upon the said amendment, at the end of
            <lb/>paragraph 161, the conclusion was that the application for
            <lb/>amendment stood dismissed. Thus, the paragraphs 157 to 161 will
            <lb/>have to be read as a whole to understand as to how the award
            <lb/>proceeds to deal with the amendment to the counter claim.
            <lb/>Paragraphs 157 to 161 of the award being relevant are reproduced
            <lb/>hereunder:
            <lb/>&quot;157. At this stage it may be noticed that the Respondent filed
            <lb/>an application dated 20.11.2019 seeking permission of the
            <lb/>Tribunal to amend the Counterclaim.
            <lb/>Claimant was
            <lb/>permitted to file reply to the same on or before 22.11.2019.
            <lb/>Claimant has filed the reply on 20.11.2019.
            <lb/>Thereafter
            <lb/>arguments in Rejoinder were heard on 27.11.2019 and
            <lb/>02.12.2019. However, no oral submissions were made on the
            <lb/>application by either party. I have considered the application
            <lb/>on the basis of the pleadings. It has been noticed earlier that
            <lb/>Respondent had issued a Notice inviting Tender on 16.01.2012
            <lb/>for &quot;…(a) Replacement of Existing twenty (20 year old 3X10
            <lb/>MW stokerfired boilers by 3X10 MW Fluidised bed
            <lb/>combustion (FBC) boilers, wherein the successful bidder will
            <lb/>made his own investment for replacement of existing stoker
            <lb/>fired boilers by FBC Boilers and associated other plant and
            <lb/>machineries including the civil works and enter into Lease
            <lb/>Agreement with ECL for running of the power plant….&quot;.
            <lb/>Therefore, it appears that the run down condition of the
            <lb/>existing stokerfires boilers had become irrelevant.
            <lb/>The
            <lb/></body>

        <page>7
            <lb/></page>

        <body>application for amendment of the counterclaim can be
            <lb/>dismissed at this stage only.
            <lb/>158. Even from the evidence on record it is evident that the
            <lb/>plant was in running condition at the time when the lease
            <lb/>expired by efflux of time. The Respondent was fully aware that
            <lb/>the plant being in running condition was wholly irrelevant, yet
            <lb/>the controversy continued even after the issuance of the NIT.
            <lb/>The NIT clearly indicates in clause 1(b) that the Power Plant is
            <lb/>offered for lease &quot;on as is where is basis&apos;&apos;. Clause 1(c) further
            <lb/>makes it clear that &quot;the existing plant is in operating
            <lb/>condition. The plant is to be operated as a Captive Power Plant
            <lb/>of ECL&quot;. In view of the above clauses, the Respondent cannot
            <lb/>now be permitted to raise a further Claim on the ground that
            <lb/>the Power Plant had to be put into running condition.
            <lb/>159. Had the possession been taken before issuing the NIT,
            <lb/>undoubtedly, the Plant was operating and therefore clearly
            <lb/>cannot be said to be not in running condition. It appears that
            <lb/>the deterioration, if any, occurred when the Claimant failed to
            <lb/>handover the possession as there was no agreement on the
            <lb/>determination of WDV of the Plant. It has come in evidence
            <lb/>that in four year&apos;s time the Plant and machinery had
            <lb/>deteriorated considerably as the Plant was lying idle. In view of
            <lb/>the detailed submissions made in this regard, on behalf of the
            <lb/>Claimant, which are noted at paragraphs 84 to 99 and the
            <lb/>reply thereto on behalf of the Respondent, which are noted in
            <lb/>paragraphs 104 till 112, it would not be possible to hold that
            <lb/>the Claimant is solely responsible for the delayed delivery of
            <lb/>possession to the Respondent. On the one hand Claimant was
            <lb/>insisting on the basis of the Clause III(a) for the determination
            <lb/>and payment of the WDV simultaneously to delivery of
            <lb/>possession. On the other hand, Respondent had demanded
            <lb/>delivery of possession much prior to the determination of the
            <lb/>WDV. Even when the WDV was determined by the
            <lb/>Respondent, it was at such a variance to the amount
            <lb/>determined by the Claimant, making it impossible for the
            <lb/>parties to reach a consensus on the WDV to be paid. In fact, as
            <lb/>noticed earlier the Claimant had filed a Writ Petition No.20948
            <lb/>of 2012. In the Calcutta High Court seeking payment of WDV
            <lb/>and handing over possession of the Plant. This Petition was
            <lb/>disposed of by the High Court on 19.03.2013. The Learned
            <lb/>Single Judge noticed &quot;…that there is a subsisting dispute as
            <lb/>regards computation of written down value in respect of the
            <lb/>additions and alterations made by the writ petitioners in
            <lb/>relation to the said generating station. It is for this reason the
            <lb/>dispute still remains unresolved. The petitioners continue to
            <lb/>remain in possession of the generating station and the
            <lb/>respondent coal company has also not taken any legal step to
            <lb/>recover possession of the station…&quot;. It is noticed by the
            <lb/>Learned Single Judge that the main prayer in the Writ Petition
            <lb/>is &quot;to prevent the respondents from obtaining recovery of
            <lb/>8
            <lb/>possession of the generating station without releasing the
            <lb/>written down value of the added assets, as per computation of
            <lb/>the petitioners.&quot; It is also noticed that in spite of orders
            <lb/>passed by the Court on 12.10.2012 that &quot;…steps ought to be
            <lb/>taken by the committee to not only physically verify the plant
            <lb/>and machinery but also other assets of the plant by
            <lb/>ascertaining the book value thereof…&quot;. no steps were taken.
            <lb/>This exercise was to be completed by 12.12.2012. Since, the
            <lb/>exercise was not completed by that time, the time was
            <lb/>extended till 08.01.2013. At the time of final disposal of the
            <lb/>Writ Petition the Learned Single Judge observed that the
            <lb/>dispute does not seem to be resolvable by the committee set
            <lb/>up by the respondent. It is noticed that the issues involved are
            <lb/>also highly disputed factual issues. The matter was therefore
            <lb/>referred to arbitration under the relevant clause of the lease
            <lb/>deed. In appeal the Division Bench upheld the order of the
            <lb/>Learned Single Judge on 19.03.2014. As noticed earlier the
            <lb/>Supreme Court referred the matter to the Sole Arbitrator by
            <lb/>order October 17, 2014, with the observation that the Sole
            <lb/>Arbitrator is &quot;to arbitrate upon the disputes&quot;. From the above,
            <lb/>it seems apparent that the reference to arbitration is not
            <lb/>limited to disputes that existed prior to the passing of the
            <lb/>order by the Supreme Court. Therefore, it cannot be accepted
            <lb/>that the reference to arbitration would not cover the Counter
            <lb/>Claims.
            <lb/>160. It must also be noticed here that the Claimant has raised
            <lb/>a preliminary objection on the ground that the application for
            <lb/>amendment suffers from delay and laches. Therefore, seeks it&apos;s
            <lb/>dismissal on this short ground. It is submitted that Claimant
            <lb/>has already filed its objection to the MECON report and also
            <lb/>filed a report submitted by M/s AKB Power Consultants Pvt.
            <lb/>Ltd. For consideration of these two reports, further evidence
            <lb/>will have to be recorded on behalf of both the parties.
            <lb/>161. It is matter of record that the application for amendment
            <lb/>was filed at the time when the Respondent was to commence
            <lb/>its arguments. In my opinion that the application cannot be
            <lb/>allowed at this stage. The amendment must be necessary for
            <lb/>the purpose of determining the real question in controversy. As
            <lb/>noticed above, the issuance of the NIT clearly demonstrates
            <lb/>the intention of the respondent was to replace the old
            <lb/>machinery and plant to Stoker Fired Boilers by Fluidised bed
            <lb/>Combustion Boilers. Therefore, the condition of the old
            <lb/>machinery as well as the question of plant being in a running
            <lb/>condition had become irrelevant. For the reasons stated above,
            <lb/>the application for amendment is dismissed as it will serve no
            <lb/>useful purpose in determining the real questions in
            <lb/>controversy between the parties.&quot;
            <lb/>9
            <lb/>10. By means of the said amendment, the ECL had claimed that the
            <lb/>power plant should be put into running condition before handing over
            <lb/>its possession. The learned Arbitrator deals with the issue in detail
            <lb/>and after considering the pleadings of the parties as also the order
            <lb/>passed by the Calcutta High Court found that the counter claim
            <lb/>sought to be raised by the said amendment regarding the plant being
            <lb/>in a running condition was irrelevant in view of the dispute raised.
            <lb/>11. The MECON report and the M/s AKB Power Consultants Pvt.
            <lb/>Ltd. report, both related to the expenses sought to be incurred in
            <lb/>bringing back the plant into running condition. Parties had filed their
            <lb/>objections to both the reports as there was substantial difference in
            <lb/>the figures indicated in the two reports. But once the Arbitrator found
            <lb/>that the amendment in the Counterclaim itself was not relevant for
            <lb/>the adjudication, there was no question of proceeding any further in
            <lb/>inviting evidence etc. with respect to the reports. The submission
            <lb/>therefore, that there is requirement of the appointment of Arbitrator to
            <lb/>carry out the exercise as per paragraph 160 of the award is therefore
            <lb/>completely untenable. The submission is based upon the misreading
            <lb/>and misrepresentation of the said paragraph, in isolation bereft of
            <lb/>preceding and succeeding paragraphs. The same is accordingly
            <lb/>rejected.
            <lb/></body>

        <page>10
            <lb/></page>

        <body>12. A bare perusal of the award, in particular paragraph 162, which
            <lb/>is the operative portion, does not in any manner indicate any kind of it
            <lb/>being an interim award or that any aspect of the matter was to be
            <lb/>further considered. In any case, the learned arbitrator did not record
            <lb/>any further observation that for leading of further evidence any date
            <lb/>has to be fixed or the parties were given opportunity to produce their
            <lb/>evidence. It was a mere submission that consideration of MECON
            <lb/>report would require further evidence but was not found to be
            <lb/>necessary by implication.
            <lb/>13. The next submission relating to the applicability of Section 33 of
            <lb/>the 1996 Act also has to fail for two reasons. Firstly, that the same is
            <lb/>neither pleaded nor prayed in the application and secondly, once the
            <lb/>Arbitrator, while awarding rent as counter claim had accepted the
            <lb/>figures as quoted by the ECL, no issue of any error on the part of the
            <lb/>Arbitrator in not correctly calculating the rent could be raised. The
            <lb/>figure as claimed by the ECL is quoted in paragraph 73(1)(ii) of the
            <lb/>award which has been accepted by the Arbitrator in the award.
            <lb/>14. There is another aspect of the matter which disentitles the
            <lb/>applicant from any relief in this application.
            <lb/>A perusal of the
            <lb/>judgment of the Delhi High Court in Section 34 of the 1996 Act
            <lb/>proceedings clearly reveals that the point which is being raised here
            <lb/>was raised before the Delhi High Court. The Delhi High Court also did
            <lb/></body>

        <page>11
            <lb/></page>

        <body>not agree with the submission of the respondentapplicant after
            <lb/>considering paragraphs 157 to 161 and proceeded to hold that the
            <lb/>observations made in paragraph 160 do not render the impugned
            <lb/>order to be interim in nature, and that the award finally decided the
            <lb/>dispute which was subject matter of the reference.
            <lb/>15. For all the reasons recorded above, the application deserves to
            <lb/>be rejected and is accordingly rejected.
            <lb/>………….........................J.
            <lb/>[VIKRAM NATH]
            <lb/>…………..........................J.
            <lb/>[M.M. SUNDRESH]
            <lb/>NEW DELHI
            <lb/>MARCH 15, 2022.
            <lb/>12
        </body>


    </text>
</tei>
