<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <page>1
            <lb/></page>

        <front>NON-REPORTABLE
            <lb/>IN THE SUPREME COURT OF INDIA
            <lb/>CRIMINAL APPELLATE JURISDICTION
            <lb/>CRIMINAL APPEAL NO.852 OF 2018
            <lb/>SARTAJ KHAN
            <lb/>.. Appellant
            <lb/>VERSUS
            <lb/>STATE OF UTTARAKHAND
            <lb/>.. Respondent
            <lb/>J U D G M E N T
            <lb/>UDAY UMESH LALIT, J.
            <lb/>1.
            <lb/>This appeal under Section 379 of the Code of Criminal Procedure,
            <lb/>1973 read with Section 2 of the Supreme Court (Enlargement of Criminal
            <lb/>Appellate Jurisdiction) Act, 1970 is directed against the judgment and order
            <lb/>dated 07.12.2017 passed by the High Court of Uttarakhand at Nainital in
            <lb/>Government Appeal No.139 of 2016.
            <lb/>2.
            <lb/>The case of the prosecution as set out in the judgment under appeal
            <lb/>was as under:
            <lb/>&quot;2. The case of the prosecution, in a nutshell, is that at 11:00 AM, S.I.
            <lb/>Manju Pandey, In-charge Human Trafficking Unit Shadra Bairaj,
            <lb/>Banbasa along with other police officials reached at Sharda Bairaj
            <lb/>near Indo-Nepal border towards eastern side to check the illicit human
            <lb/></front>
            
            <note place="footnote">
            <lb/>Digitally signed by Dr.
            <lb/>Mukesh Nasa
            <lb/>Date: 2022.03.26
            <lb/>08:47:56 IST
            <lb/>Reason:
            <lb/>Signature Not Verified
</note>
        <page>2
            <lb/></page>

        <body>trafficking. One volunteer namely Meera Sauda was also with them.
            <lb/>They were checking the people coming from Nepal border. At about
            <lb/>13:30 hours, a secret information was received that an Indian boy was
            <lb/>trying to import a minor girl of Nepal origin for the purpose of
            <lb/>exploitation. The information was acted upon and one girl was noticed
            <lb/>near a cart selling snacks towards the eastern side of Sharda Barrage.
            <lb/>The name of the girl was ascertained. She disclosed her name &quot;X X
            <lb/>X&quot; 1 R/o Village Koteshwar, District Kathmandu, Nepal, aged about 15
            <lb/>years. The investigation was carried out by maintaining all decency
            <lb/>through Meera Sauda, who was well conversant with Hindi and Nepali
            <lb/>languages. She disclosed to the police party that on 10.04.2015, she
            <lb/>came all alone to see her uncle namely Arjun Sharma, who was a
            <lb/>teacher in Lamki (Nepal). On 11.04.2015 at about 10:00 AM, she was
            <lb/>having ice-cream from a cart at Atariya Bus stand. A boy came and
            <lb/>stood by her side. He also started having the ice-cream. He tried to
            <lb/>entice her. He allured her that he would take her to Banbasa in India
            <lb/>where she can do shopping. They would stay in a hotel at Banbasa and
            <lb/>in the morning, he would send her back to Atariya, Nepal. She trusted
            <lb/>him. The boy brought her from Atariya, Nepal to Mahendra Nagar. He
            <lb/>started pressing her breast in the bus. She told him not to do so.
            <lb/>Thereafter, at Mahendra Nagar, he made her to sit on a horse cart,
            <lb/>which was going towards India. They reached Banbasa bridge at about
            <lb/>13:45 hours. The gate was closed. Many horse carts and vehicles were
            <lb/>parked. There was lot of rush. The boy got down from the horse cart
            <lb/>and told her that there was police checking. He tutored her to tell the
            <lb/>police that she was going to Banbasa for shopping. He started walking
            <lb/>ahead. He told her that he would see her after some distance.
            <lb/>Thereafter, they searched the boy. They reached near canal gate. The
            <lb/>boy was standing near the tree facing towards bridge. &quot;X X X&quot;
            <lb/>recognized the boy and told that he was the same boy, who has enticed
            <lb/>her to come from Nepal. The boy was arrested. He disclosed his name
            <lb/>Sartaj Khan, S/o Sardar Khan, R/o Mohalla Bhure Khan, P.S.
            <lb/>Khakhra, District Pilibhit, Uttar Pradesh. He was aged 30 years. He
            <lb/>admitted his guilt. The respondent and girl were brought to the office
            <lb/>for counseling. Other police officials also reached the spot. It was,
            <lb/>primafacie, found that the boy had brought the girl to India for
            <lb/>exploitation. The personal search of the respondent was carried out.
            <lb/>One pocket diary, one packet of condom, two man force tablets,
            <lb/>Indian and Nepal currency and two mobile phones were found from
            <lb/>his possession. The seizure memo was prepared. One copy of the same
            <lb/>was handed over to the respondent. PW2 &quot;X X X&quot; was medically
            <lb/>examined by PW4 Dr. Vinod Kumar Joshi.
            <lb/>3. The FIR was registered. The investigation was carried out and the
            <lb/>challan was put up after completing all the codal formalities.
            <lb/></body>
            <note place="footnote">

                <lb/>1 Identity of the prosecutrix/victim is not being disclosed.
            </note>

        <page>3
            <lb/></page>

        <body>4. The prosecution has examined as many as six witnesses in its
            <lb/>support.
            <lb/>5. Thereafter, the statement of respondent was recorded under Section
            <lb/>313 of Cr.P.C. He denied the case of the prosecution. According to
            <lb/>him, he was falsely implicated.&quot;
            <lb/>3.
            <lb/>The appellant was tried in the Court of Special Sessions Judge,
            <lb/>Champawat, in Special Sessions Trial No.07 of 2015 for having committed
            <lb/>the offence punishable under Sections 363, 366-B, 370(4), 506 of the
            <lb/>Indian Penal Code, 1860 (&quot;IPC&quot; for short) and Section 8 of the POCSO
            <lb/>Act,
            <lb/>4.
            <lb/>In support of its case, the prosecution relied upon the testimony of
            <lb/>PW1 Manju Pandey, who along with PW3 Meera Saud had initially
            <lb/>interacted with the victim who was examined as PW2. The evidence of
            <lb/>PW3 Meera Saud was as under:
            <lb/>&quot;That on 11.04.2015, I was present in my office. S.I. Manju Pandey,
            <lb/>Constable Bhuvan Rana, Constable Laxman Chand, constable Ganesh
            <lb/>Singh Bisht and constable Ravi Joshi and driver Heera Singh were
            <lb/>also present. We all were carrying out checking. The gate for the entry
            <lb/>to Nepal was closed. It was abouf 1 :00 or 1½ pm. It was day time. We
            <lb/>reached a little towards Nepal. Some person came to meet Manju
            <lb/>Pandey and told that one girl is standing near the cart. We all went
            <lb/>near to the said chaat stall.
            <lb/>The chaat cart was in front towards of the custom office. I know
            <lb/>Nepalese language. One girl about 14-15 years old was standing near
            <lb/>the chaat cart. When I asked the name and address of the said girl in
            <lb/>Nepalese language then she told her name is &quot;X X X&quot; and she is
            <lb/>resident of Koteshwar, Kathmandu. And she told that on 10.04.2015
            <lb/>she was coming to Lamki in a bus from Kathmandu (Nepal) to meet
            <lb/>her uncle and when she reached Atariya she was standing and having
            <lb/>ice-cream from a cart and then she met with a boy who asked her to
            <lb/></body>

        <page>4
            <lb/></page>

        <body>come to Banbasa, and he would make her roaming and shopping and
            <lb/>would send her back to Atariya.
            <lb/>Thereafter we both boarded on a bus to Mahindra Nagar from there.
            <lb/>Then we reached Mahindra Nagar. That boy fed me food in Mahindra
            <lb/>Nagar. Thereafter we sat on a horse cart to India from Mahindra Nagar
            <lb/>bus stand. When we reached towards Nepal in Banbasa then this boy
            <lb/>asked me to stay there as the checking is going on ahead and he will
            <lb/>meet me ahead. She told that she does not know the name of the boy.
            <lb/>She can recognise after seeing him.
            <lb/>Thereafter, we all along with the girl came towards the canal after
            <lb/>crossing the bridge in Manju Pandey&apos;s vehicle. When we reached at
            <lb/>canal gate then the said girl pointed towards a boy and said that this is
            <lb/>the same boy who is standing with his face towards canal and brought
            <lb/>me. Thereafter the said boy was encircled and apprehended by the
            <lb/>policemen and was taken to the Manju Pandey&apos;s office. A counselling
            <lb/>was conducted there. After some time, Circle Officer and the Project
            <lb/>Director Mr. Janak Chand, and Secretary Bhuvan Chand Gadkoti from
            <lb/>our office came there. The CO reached in one hour and the officers
            <lb/>from our office reached in 20-25 minutes.
            <lb/>Thereafter, when people from our society in Nepalese and CO made
            <lb/>inquiry with &quot;X X X&quot; then she told the same thing as mentioned
            <lb/>above. And a document of joint inquiry was prepared. We all put our
            <lb/>signatures on it. It is marked as Exhibit Ka-1 on the record. it is
            <lb/>verified by me today. Thereafter the lady sub inspector prepared the
            <lb/>memo of recovery of the prosecutrix and memo of arrest of the
            <lb/>accused after arresting the accused. It was signed by the policemen
            <lb/>and the people who were present at the time of the counselling. It is
            <lb/>identified by me today. It is marked as exhibit Ka-2. The CO did not
            <lb/>sign it. Manju Pandey had searched the accused. And she sealed the
            <lb/>articles such as mobile etc. which was recovered from him.
            <lb/>Thereafter we went to police station Banbasa along with the
            <lb/>prosecutrix and. the accused with policemen. The sub inspector got
            <lb/>the report registered and handed over the prosecutrix and the accused
            <lb/>to the police station.&quot;
            <lb/>5.
            <lb/>As regards the age of the victim, PW4 Dr. Vinod Kumar Joshi, who
            <lb/>was one of the Members of the Board which had medically examined her,
            <lb/>stated as under:
            <lb/>&quot;The prosecutrix was medically fit in my opinion. Thereafter, on the
            <lb/></body>

        <page>5
            <lb/></page>

        <body>basis of the report with regard to the age of &quot;X X X&quot; received from
            <lb/>CMO Udham Singh Nagar by SI Meenakshi Nautiyal, PS Loha Ghat
            <lb/>which is document no. 5Ka/16 5Ka/18, report of Radiologist district
            <lb/>hospital Udham Singh Nagar on X-Ray from is document no. 5Ka/17
            <lb/>which is perused by CMO Udham Singh Nagar and the report of
            <lb/>dental surgeon district hospital Udham Singh Nagar which is
            <lb/>document no. 5Ka/19, one supplementary report with regard to the age
            <lb/>of &quot;X X X&quot; was prepared by me which is document no.5Ka/22. On
            <lb/>which I found the age of &quot;X X X&quot; to be about 17 years old. On which,
            <lb/>I identify my handwriting and signature and the signature of SI
            <lb/>Meenakshi Nautiyal. It is marked as exhibit Ka-6.&quot;
            <lb/>6.
            <lb/>The Trial Court having acquitted the appellant of the charges levelled
            <lb/>against him, the State of Uttarakhand preferred the Government Appeal
            <lb/>No.139 of 2016 challenging the acquittal.
            <lb/>7.
            <lb/>After considering the material on record and the rival submissions,
            <lb/>the High Court found that the Trial Court had not considered the material
            <lb/>evidence on record. Having analyzed the reasons which had weighed with
            <lb/>the Trial Court, the High Court found that the decision of the Trial Court
            <lb/>was perverse and the case of the prosecution deserved to be accepted.
            <lb/>Allowing the appeal vide its judgment under appeal, the High Court set-<lb/>aside the order of acquittal and convicted the appellant of the offences
            <lb/>punishable under Sections 363, 366-B, 370(4) and 506 of the IPC, and
            <lb/>under Section 8 of the POCSO Act. He was awarded substantive sentence
            <lb/>of 7 years imprisonment under the first, imprisonment for 10 years under
            <lb/>the second, imprisonment for 10 years under the third, and, imprisonment
            <lb/>for one year under the fourth count of the offences punishable under the
            <lb/></body>

        <page>6
            <lb/></page>

        <body>IPC. In respect of the offence punishable under Section 8 of the POCSO
            <lb/>Act, he was awarded imprisonment for three years. All the sentences were
            <lb/>to run concurrently.
            <lb/>8.
            <lb/>Being aggrieved, the instant appeal has been preferred.
            <lb/>9.
            <lb/>We have heard Mr. Jitendra Mohan Sharma, learned Senior
            <lb/>Advocate in support of the appeal, and, Mr. Jatinder Kumar Bhatia, learned
            <lb/>Advocate for the State.
            <lb/>10. Mr. Jitendra Mohan Sharma, learned Senior Advocate submits inter
            <lb/>alia:
            <lb/>(a)
            <lb/>The requirements under Section 188 of the Code of Criminal
            <lb/>Procedure, 1973 were not satisfied and no sanction in terms of said
            <lb/>Section was placed on record; and that in the absence of such
            <lb/>sanction, the appellant could not have been tried.
            <lb/>(b) There was no allurement which was extended by the appellant and
            <lb/>the victim had gone from Kathmandu to Atariya covering the
            <lb/>distance of more than 650 kms. on her own.
            <lb/>(c) The age of the victim was definitely beyond 18 years of age and, as
            <lb/>such, the offence would not come under Section 370(4) of the IPC.
            <lb/></body>

        <page>7
            <lb/></page>

        <body>11. The submissions are countered by Mr. Jatinder Kumar Bhatia,
            <lb/>learned counsel for the State. He strongly submits that the view taken by
            <lb/>the High Court does not call for any interference.
            <lb/>12. Section 188 of the Code is to the following effect:
            <lb/>&quot;188. Offence committed outside India.-When an offence is
            <lb/>committed outside India-<lb/>(a) by a citizen of India, whether on the high seas or elsewhere; or
            <lb/>(b) by a person, not being such citizen, on any ship or aircraft
            <lb/>registered in India,
            <lb/>he may be dealt with in respect of such offence as if it had been
            <lb/>committed at any place within India at which he may be found:
            <lb/>Provided that, notwithstanding anything in any of the preceding
            <lb/>sections of this Chapter, no such offence shall be inquired into or tried
            <lb/>in India except with the previous sanction of the Central
            <lb/>Government.&quot;
            <lb/>13. In terms of Section 188, even if an offence is committed outside
            <lb/>India, (a) by a citizen whether on the high seas or anywhere else or (b) by a
            <lb/>non-citizen on a ship or aircraft registered in India, the offence can still be
            <lb/>tried in India provided the conditions mentioned in said Section are
            <lb/>satisfied. The Section gets attracted when the entirety of the offence is
            <lb/>committed outside India; and the grant of sanction would enable such
            <lb/>offence to be enquired into or tried in India.
            <lb/></body>

        <page>8
            <lb/></page>

        <body>14. As the facts and circumstances of the case indicate, a part of the
            <lb/>offence was definitely committed on the soil of this country and as such
            <lb/>going by the normal principles the offence could be looked into and tried
            <lb/>by Indian courts. Since the offence was not committed in its entirety,
            <lb/>outside India, the matter would not come within the scope of Section 188
            <lb/>of the Code and there was no necessity of any sanction as mandated by the
            <lb/>proviso to Section 188. We, therefore, reject the first submission advanced
            <lb/>by Mr. Sharma.
            <lb/>15. Coming to the second submission, it is true that the victim had
            <lb/>traveled on her own from Kathmandu to Atariya. However, the evidence
            <lb/>on record completely establishes that she was lured into coming to India.
            <lb/>The offences alleged against the appellant were thus rightly invoked and
            <lb/>fully substantiated.
            <lb/>16. As regards the third submission, the evidence on record is absolutely
            <lb/>clear that the age of the victim was below 18 years of age. The medical
            <lb/>board had not only done the radiological tests but had also undertaken
            <lb/>dental test on the basis of which her age was found to be below 18 years.
            <lb/>17. In the circumstances, sub-section 4 of Section 370 IPC would
            <lb/>definitely get attracted. Said Section 370(4) postulates minimum sentence
            <lb/></body>

        <page>9
            <lb/></page>

        <body>of 10 years. Viewed thus, the sentences awarded to the appellant cannot be
            <lb/>termed to be excessive on any count.
            <lb/>18. We, therefore, see no reason to take a different view in the matter.
            <lb/>Affirming the view taken by the High Court, we dismiss the appeal.
            <lb/>19. The appellant shall serve out the sentence awarded to him.
            <lb/>…………………………………………….J.
            <lb/>(UDAY UMESH LALIT)
            <lb/>…………………………………………….J.
            <lb/>(S. RAVINDRA BHAT)
            <lb/>…………………………………………….J.
            <lb/>(PAMIDIGHANTAM SRI NARASIMHA)
            <lb/>New Delhi;
            <lb/>March 24, 2022.
        </body>


    </text>
</tei>
